<ROOT>
  <POLIDOC LABEL="CSA Staff Notice">
    <POLIDENT>
      <N></N>
      <TI></TI>
      <DATE></DATE>
    </POLIDENT>
    <FREEFORM>
      <BLOCK1>
        <TI></TI>
        <P>-1-</P>
        <BLOCK1>
          <TI></TI>
          <P>
            <BOLD>CSA Staff Notice 51-362
<EM>Staff Review of COVID-19 Disclosures and Guide for Disclosure
Improvements</EM></BOLD>
          </P>
          <BLOCK1>
            <TI></TI>
            <P>
              <BOLD>February 25, 2021</BOLD>
            </P>
            <BLOCK1>
              <TI></TI>
              <P>
                <BOLD>Introduction</BOLD>
              </P>
              <BLOCK1>
                <TI></TI>
                <P>The Canadian Securities Administrators (<BOLD>CSA</BOLD>) have prepared this Staff Notice (<BOLD>Notice</BOLD>) to report the
results of recently completed continuous disclosure reviews (<BOLD>reviews</BOLD>) conducted by CSA staff (<BOLD>staff or
we</BOLD>) of the disclosures provided by reporting issuers<SUP>1</SUP> on the impact of COVID-19 to their business. Since
the World Health Organization declared COVID-19 as a pandemic on March 11, 2020, COVID-19 has
had a material adverse impact on the economy and is posing widespread business challenges for many
issuers, including reporting on and disclosing the business impact of COVID-19.</P>
                <BLOCK1>
                  <TI></TI>
                  <P>This issue-oriented review assessed compliance of issuers’ disclosures of the current and anticipated
impacts related to COVID-19 on their respective operations, financial condition, liquidity and future
prospects. The reviews also assessed key financial reporting areas applicable to issuers that may be
subject to significant judgement and measurement uncertainty in the current environment.</P>
                  <BLOCK1>
                    <TI></TI>
                    <P>We recognize that issuers are preparing disclosure in a rapidly changing environment. However,
meaningful disclosures about the business impacts and potential uncertainties regarding COVID-19 are
needed for investors to make informed investment decisions. This Notice summarizes our key review
findings and includes some disclosure examples and guidance to assist reporting issuers and their advisors
with disclosing and reporting on the impact of COVID-19 to their business and operations.</P>
                    <BLOCK1>
                      <TI></TI>
                      <P>We will continue to closely monitor issuers’ continuous disclosure (<BOLD>CD</BOLD>) filings in relation to the impact
of the COVID-19 pandemic as part of our ongoing CSA CD review program. For further details, see CSA
Staff Notice 51-312 (revised) <EM>Harmonized Continuous Disclosure Review Program</EM><SUP>2</SUP><EM>.</EM> An issuer’s
disclosure relating to the impacts and risk factors of the COVID-19 pandemic may also be assessed as
part of staff’s review of prospectus filings in connection with public offerings.</P>
                      <BLOCK1>
                        <TI></TI>
                        <P>1 In this Notice “issuers” means those reporting issuers contemplated in National Instrument 51-102 <EM>Continuous Disclosure
Obligations</EM> (<BOLD>NI 51-102</BOLD>).</P>
                        <BLOCK1>
                          <TI></TI>
                          <P>2 Additional regulatory guidance on COVID-19 can be accessed at the CSA COVID-19 Information Hub at
https://www.securities-administrators.ca/aboutcsa.aspx?id=1885.</P>
                        </BLOCK1>
                      </BLOCK1>
                    </BLOCK1>
                  </BLOCK1>
                </BLOCK1>
              </BLOCK1>
            </BLOCK1>
          </BLOCK1>
        </BLOCK1>
      </BLOCK1>
    </FREEFORM>
  </POLIDOC>
</ROOT>