<ROOT>
  <POLIDOC LABEL="CSA Staff Notice">
    <POLIDENT>
      <N></N>
      <TI>R. v. Chouhan
          
        
        
          : Signs of Seismic Shift in Jury Selection</TI>
      <DATE></DATE>
    </POLIDENT>
    <FREEFORM>
      <BLOCK1>
        <TI>R. v. Chouhan
          
        
        
          : Signs of Seismic Shift in Jury Selection</TI>
        <P>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPSMT" font-size="12.00pt">Steve Coughlan</FONT>
        </P>
      </BLOCK1>
      <BLOCK1>
        <TI>Schulich School of Law, Dalhousie University</TI>
        <P>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPS-ItalicMT" font-size="12.00pt">
            <EM>Chouhan</EM>
          </FONT>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPSMT" font-size="12.00pt">is a challenging decision, but understandably so, given the challenging issues it poses.
The Court indicated the</FONT>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPS-ItalicMT" font-size="12.00pt">
            <EM>result</EM>
          </FONT>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPSMT" font-size="12.00pt">in the case on the date they heard the appeal. This was
appropriate, since both issues in the case – whether the abolition of peremptory challenges
violated the</FONT>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPS-ItalicMT" font-size="12.00pt">
            <EM>Charter</EM>
          </FONT>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPSMT" font-size="12.00pt">, and even if did not whether that change applied retrospectively – were
something of a time bomb ticking away in the heart of the jury system. It was another eight
months before the reasons for that result were issued, and those reasons show some fundamental
divides in the Court. At the most basic level this is reflected in the presence of five different sets
of reasons among the nine judges deciding.</FONT>
        </P>
        <P>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPSMT" font-size="12.00pt">This division is also understandable, given the context. The jury system has long been based on
certain presuppositions about impartiality and representativeness: the changes to the</FONT>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPS-ItalicMT" font-size="12.00pt">
            <EM>Criminal
Code</EM>
          </FONT>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPSMT" font-size="12.00pt">of which the abolition of peremptory challenges were a part are in many ways at odds with
those presuppositions. We are at a stage of flux, not only in the actual legislation, but in the
underlying understandings and assumptions to be applied to that legislation. The divided result in</FONT>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPS-ItalicMT" font-size="12.00pt">
            <EM>Chouhan</EM>
          </FONT>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPSMT" font-size="12.00pt">suggests that we are on the verge of a seismic shift which could result in a very
different jury selection process in future.</FONT>
        </P>
        <P>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPSMT" font-size="12.00pt">Given the fractured nature of the result in</FONT>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPS-ItalicMT" font-size="12.00pt">
            <EM>Chouhan</EM>
          </FONT>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPSMT" font-size="12.00pt">, and particularly the fact that no individual
judgement has more than three signatories, it is important to be clear from the start as to exactly
what views constitute the majority opinion, and which do not. The</FONT>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPS-ItalicMT" font-size="12.00pt">
            <EM>hub</EM>
          </FONT>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPSMT" font-size="12.00pt">of all the decisions is that
of Justices Moldaver and Brown, since the other judgments all situate themselves in relation to it.
However, it is not straightforwardly the case that that judgement is the majority one: it is on
some issues, but not on others.</FONT>
        </P>
        <P>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPSMT" font-size="12.00pt">First, there is a clear majority that the abolition of peremptory challenges does not, at a bottom
line level, violate either section 11(d) or section 11(f). Justices Moldaver and Brown reach that
conclusion in reasons written for themselves and Chief Justice Wagner. Justice Rowe adopts
those reasons but adds additional observations of his own. Those “hub” reasons therefore have,
in their entirety, the support of four of the nine judges deciding. Four other judges agree with the</FONT>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPS-ItalicMT" font-size="12.00pt">
            <EM>conclusion</EM>
          </FONT>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPSMT" font-size="12.00pt">that there are no section 11(d) or 11(f) violations: Justice Martin writes for herself
and Justices Karakatsanis and Kasirer, while Justice Abella writes sole reasons, but both those
judgments adopt the hub reasons on that point. The official reporter describes Justice Martin’s
reasons as “concurring” ones, which is accurate to a point, though as we will see below there is
an extremely important caveat. Justice Abella independently (and briefly) concludes that the
legislation is “constitutionally compliant” (para 153), though Justices Moldaver and Brown note
that “the substance of her reasons actually supports the opposite conclusion” (para 44).</FONT>
        </P>
        <P>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPSMT" font-size="12.00pt">There is also a clear majority that the abolition of peremptory challenges had retrospective effect:
without caveat, seven judges ascribe to Justices Moldaver and Brown’s reasons in that regard.
Justices Abella and Côté dissent on that point, for separate but not unrelated reasons.</FONT>
        </P>
        <P>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPSMT" font-size="12.00pt">There is also a majority opinion on</FONT>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPS-ItalicMT" font-size="12.00pt">
            <EM>some</EM>
          </FONT>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPSMT" font-size="12.00pt">of the reasons that there is no section 11(d) or 11(f)
violation. Indeed, it is easy to argue that the nine judges are unanimous on one point: that judges
in jury trials need to do</FONT>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPS-ItalicMT" font-size="12.00pt">
            <EM>more</EM>
          </FONT>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPSMT" font-size="12.00pt">to combat unconscious biases and discrimination and to protect</FONT>
        </P>
        <P>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPSMT" font-size="12.00pt">impartiality and representativeness. It is only because of disagreement over how</FONT>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPS-ItalicMT" font-size="12.00pt">
            <EM>much</EM>
          </FONT>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPSMT" font-size="12.00pt">more, and
whether that is sufficient, that the need for different sets of reasons arises.</FONT>
        </P>
        <P>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPSMT" font-size="12.00pt">Justices Moldaver and Brown’s reason largely depend on the presence of other mechanisms to
achieve those goals, concluding that they are sufficient, even in the absence of peremptory
challenges, to protect impartiality. These include instructions to juries about unconscious bias,
both in general and as they arise from the specifics of the case, so that jurors can avoid acting on
unconscious assumptions. Justice Martin’s cohort specifically supports that part of the reasoning,
so it has unambiguous majority support.</FONT>
        </P>
        <P>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPSMT" font-size="12.00pt">However, Justices Moldaver and Brown also support their conclusion that the absence of
peremptory challenges is not fatal based on two other mechanisms in the jury selection process:
challenges for cause, and the amendment to the stand-aside power allowing it to be used for the
purpose of maintaining public confidence in the administration of justice. On the one hand we
could look at the pure numbers here. Justice Martin’s cohort, at para 112, explicitly declines to
decide based on the use of those powers:</FONT>
        </P>
        <P>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPSMT" font-size="12.00pt">These issues are complex, multifaceted and immaterial to the outcome of this appeal. In
my view, it is preferable not to address them here given the lack of direct assistance from
the parties and scant jurisprudence from the lower courts on this matter.</FONT>
        </P>
        <P>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPSMT" font-size="12.00pt">Justice Côté, of course, dissents from the conclusion of Justices Moldaver and Brown, while
Justice Abella writes her own reasons (which Justices Moldaver and Brown felt supported the
opposite side), so it would be tempting to conclude that the hub decision has the support of only
four out of nine judges. In a sense that is correct, but not for the reason that that sounds like: the
real point is that five of the nine judges seem inclined to go</FONT>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPS-ItalicMT" font-size="12.00pt">
            <EM>further</EM>
          </FONT>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPSMT" font-size="12.00pt">than Justices Moldaver and
Brown in expanding the use of challenge for cause and stand-asides.</FONT>
        </P>
        <P>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPSMT" font-size="12.00pt">This is especially noteworthy given that Justice Moldaver and Brown would already be
expanding the power of challenge for cause from its current state, and give a relatively expansive
reading to the amended stand-aside power. We shall look at each separately.</FONT>
        </P>
        <P>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPSMT" font-size="12.00pt">With regard to challenge for cause, Justices Moldaver and Brown both explicitly and implicitly
expand the power. Noting that the ability to challenge for cause had already been broadened in
the cases of bias based on race, and pointing to “growing knowledge of the ways in which
unconscious bias can affect the impartiality of a juror”, they acknowledge that “a wide range of
characteristics — not just race — can create a risk of prejudice and discrimination, and are the
proper subject of questioning on a challenge for cause” (para 61). That is an explicit expansion
of the power, but they also talk about the power as one more easily available than might have
been thought. They say:</FONT>
        </P>
        <P>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPSMT" font-size="12.00pt">[62] While widespread bias cannot be presumed in all cases, the parties do not face an
onerous burden for raising a challenge for cause. The accused person or the Crown must
merely demonstrate a reasonable possibility that bias or prejudicial attitudes exist in the
community, with respect to relevant characteristics of the accused or victim, and could
taint the impartiality of the jurors. In most cases, expert evidence will not be necessary:
challenges for cause must be available wherever the experience of the trial judge, in
consultation with counsel, dictates that, in the case before them, a realistic potential for
partiality arises.</FONT>
        </P>
        <P>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPSMT" font-size="12.00pt">Suggesting that there is not an “onerous burden” in challenge for cause seems to indicate an
implicit shift in attitude. Justices Moldaver and Brown cite</FONT>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPS-ItalicMT" font-size="12.00pt">
            <EM>R. v. Spence</EM>
          </FONT>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPSMT" font-size="12.00pt">, 2005 SCC 71,</FONT>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPS-ItalicMT" font-size="12.00pt">
            <EM>R. v.
Williams</EM>
          </FONT>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPSMT" font-size="12.00pt">, [1998] 1 S.C.R. 1128, and</FONT>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPS-ItalicMT" font-size="12.00pt">
            <EM>R. v. Find</EM>
          </FONT>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPSMT" font-size="12.00pt">, 2001 SCC 32 for this view, but one could easily
argue that the opposite attitude is more reflected in those decisions. In</FONT>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPS-ItalicMT" font-size="12.00pt">
            <EM>Spence</EM>
          </FONT>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPSMT" font-size="12.00pt">, for example, the
Court seemed far less open to the view that a trial judge’s experience should be sufficient:</FONT>
        </P>
        <P>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPSMT" font-size="12.00pt">[6]…The eventual logic of the defence argument, it seems, is that courts should take
judicial notice of a “realistic possibility” of racial partiality in every case where the
jurors, accused, complainant and witnesses are not all of the same race. Might this race-
centred view of the jury system be pushed into other areas of discrimination? Do
Catholics or Hindus more readily believe witnesses who are disclosed to be of the same
faith? Do male jurors “empathize” more with male complainants than with female
complainants? Does this empathy translate into real (or reasonably perceived) bias? Is
race a more powerful motivator than these other sources of potential bias? Our traditional
belief was that the diversity of 12 jurors would iron out and diffuse such individual
variations.</FONT>
        </P>
        <P>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPSMT" font-size="12.00pt">[7] In my view, with respect, the majority judgment of the Ontario Court of Appeal in
this case pushed judicial notice beyond its proper limits. The respondent’s argument
proceeded on the basis of questions to which neither evidence, nor judicial notice
properly taken, supplied answers.</FONT>
        </P>
        <P>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPSMT" font-size="12.00pt">Similarly</FONT>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPS-ItalicMT" font-size="12.00pt">
            <EM>Williams</EM>
          </FONT>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPSMT" font-size="12.00pt">seemed more concerned, outside the context of racial prejudice, with the trial
judge’s role as a gatekeeper:</FONT>
        </P>
        <P>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPSMT" font-size="12.00pt">[13]…The judge has a wide discretion in controlling the challenge process, to prevent its
abuse, to ensure it is fair to the prospective juror as well as the accused, and to prevent
the trial from being unnecessarily delayed by unfounded challenges for cause.</FONT>
        </P>
        <P>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPSMT" font-size="12.00pt">Like</FONT>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPS-ItalicMT" font-size="12.00pt">
            <EM>Williams</EM>
          </FONT>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPSMT" font-size="12.00pt">,</FONT>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPS-ItalicMT" font-size="12.00pt">
            <EM>Find</EM>
          </FONT>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPSMT" font-size="12.00pt">also contrasted the more open challenge for process in the United States
with that in Canada. Noting the presumption of impartiality in Canada, the Court held:</FONT>
        </P>
        <P>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPSMT" font-size="12.00pt">[26]…This presumption is displaced only where potential bias is either clear and obvious
(addressed by judicial pre-screening), or where the accused or prosecution shows reason
to suspect that members of the jury array may possess biases that cannot be set aside
(addressed by the challenge for cause process).</FONT>
        </P>
        <P>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPSMT" font-size="12.00pt">So the decision of Justices Moldaver and Brown, setting the minimum, see challenge for cause as
much more readily available than in the past when dealing with unconscious bias, even when
based on factors other than race. Although there were statutory changes to the challenge for
cause process – most notably that the trier of the challenge is now the trial judge personally –
those changes did not necessitate this shift: it is a change in attitude.</FONT>
        </P>
        <P>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPSMT" font-size="12.00pt">The change to the stand-aside power, on the other hand, was explicitly motivated by the new
wording in section 633: the power to have potential jurors stand aside for the purpose of
“maintaining public confidence in the administration of justice”. Justices Moldaver and Brown
note that one possible use for this new power would be to exclude a juror who survived a
challenge for cause but whom the judge, accused, or Crown nonetheless believe might be partial.
Beyond that, they say that the contours of the power should be worked out on a case-by-case
basis. Most importantly – and this is where it matters most that this portion of their judgment</FONT>
        </P>
        <P>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPSMT" font-size="12.00pt">does not have majority support – they offer observations about what the power should</FONT>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPS-ItalicMT" font-size="12.00pt">
            <EM>not</EM>
          </FONT>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPSMT" font-size="12.00pt">be
used for: “we cannot accept that public confidence in the administration of justice depends on
achieving a jury that approximates the diversity of Canadian society” (para 74).</FONT>
        </P>
        <P>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPSMT" font-size="12.00pt">In adopting that view, Justices Moldaver and Brown are simply stating the current orthodoxy.
The view espoused in many prior decisions is that in, for example,</FONT>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPS-ItalicMT" font-size="12.00pt">
            <EM>R. v. Kokopenace</EM>
          </FONT>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPSMT" font-size="12.00pt">, 2015 SCC
28, that “[c]ourts have consistently rejected the idea that an accused is entitled to a particular
number of individuals of his or her race on either the jury roll or petit jury” (para 39) or
“representativeness is not about targeting particular groups for inclusion on the jury roll” (para
61). Perhaps the key thing to recognize in</FONT>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPS-ItalicMT" font-size="12.00pt">
            <EM>Chouhan</EM>
          </FONT>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPSMT" font-size="12.00pt">is the possibility that that orthodoxy is
crumbling.</FONT>
        </P>
        <P>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPSMT" font-size="12.00pt">Justice Martin’s cohort, for example, declined to adopt the hub decision’s approach to challenge
for cause or to the stand-aside power on the basis that the issues did not need to be decided. They
did offer some preliminary thoughts on the issue, however, which expressed concern that Justice
Moldaver and Brown were too</FONT>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPS-ItalicMT" font-size="12.00pt">
            <EM>limited</EM>
          </FONT>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPSMT" font-size="12.00pt">in their approach. With regard to using the stand-aside
power to achieve representativeness, for example, they held:</FONT>
        </P>
        <P>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPSMT" font-size="12.00pt">[115]…Random selection from broad-based lists was established as a constitutional
minimum in</FONT>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPS-ItalicMT" font-size="12.00pt">
            <EM>R. v. Kokopenace</EM>
          </FONT>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPSMT" font-size="12.00pt">, 2015 SCC 28, [2015] 2 S.C.R. 398</FONT>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPS-ItalicMT" font-size="12.00pt">
            <EM>.</EM>
          </FONT>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPSMT" font-size="12.00pt">However, that case
did not address whether Parliament could implement further measures for assuring
representativeness and impartiality, including measures to deliberately</FONT>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPS-ItalicMT" font-size="12.00pt">
            <EM>include</EM>
          </FONT>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPSMT" font-size="12.00pt">underrepresented groups. As long as such measures comply with the Constitution, the
only question is what Parliament intended.</FONT>
        </P>
        <P>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPSMT" font-size="12.00pt">With regard to challenge for cause, Justice Martin notes that:</FONT>
        </P>
        <P>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPSMT" font-size="12.00pt">120 … With good reason, this Court has explicitly declined to adopt the kind of highly
intrusive questioning for challenges for cause that can be seen in the United States (</FONT>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPS-ItalicMT" font-size="12.00pt">
            <EM>Find</EM>
          </FONT>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPSMT" font-size="12.00pt">,
at para. 27). Yet privacy is just one interest to be weighed against others…</FONT>
        </P>
        <P>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPSMT" font-size="12.00pt">Similarly Justice Abella would go further than the hub decision. She puts forward the view that
“[t]he new robust challenge for cause process will require more probing questions than have
traditionally been asked to properly screen for subconscious stereotypes and assumptions” (para
160) and that judges should ask “questions that they believe, based on their common sense and
judicial experience, will assist in rooting out biases” (para 161). She also finds that the amended
stand-aside power “gives trial judges the discretion ‘to make room for a more diverse jury’”
(para 163).</FONT>
        </P>
        <P>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPSMT" font-size="12.00pt">Justice Côté, of course, dissented on whether the abolition of peremptory challenges violated
section 11(f), and her reasons for doing so puts her squarely in the camp of Justices Martin and
Abella on how “representativeness” should be understood:</FONT>
        </P>
        <P>
          <FONT font-name="TimesNewRomanPSMT" font-size="12.00pt">[274] …The uncontested evidence before the trial judge in the present case indicated that
peremptory challenges were used by racialized persons to attempt to empanel more
diverse juries …. The abolition of peremptory challenges therefore removes a tool often
used by racialized and other marginalized persons to improve the representativeness of
juries, in support of at least two elements of the benefit of trial by jury: the jury’s role as
the conscience of the community and public trust in the justice system.</FONT>
        </P>
      </BLOCK1>
    </FREEFORM>
  </POLIDOC>
</ROOT>