<ROOT>
<POLIDOC LABEL="CSA Staff Notice">
<POLIDENT>
<N>
</N>
<TI>OECD Economic Surveys:
Canada
2021</TI>
<DATE>
</DATE>
</POLIDENT>
<FREEFORM>
<BLOCK1>
<TI>OECD Economic Surveys:
Canada
2021</TI>
<BLOCK2>
<TI>BASIC STATISTICS OF CANADA, 2019
 1</TI>
<IMAGE>
</IMAGE>
<P>
<BOLD>
<FONT font-name="ArialNarrow-Bold" font-size="36.00pt">Executive Summary</FONT>
</BOLD>
</P>
<P>
<BOLD>
<FONT font-name="Arial-BoldMT" font-size="12.00pt">Canada’s vaccine rollout is bringing
the prospect of an end to the crisis</FONT>
</BOLD>
</P>
<P>
<BOLD>
<FONT font-name="Arial-BoldMT" font-size="9.96pt">Vaccine rollout is underway, but contagion
remains an issue and confinement measures
are still in place.</FONT>
</BOLD>
<FONT font-name="ArialMT" font-size="9.96pt">Overall, Canada’s COVID-19
related fatalities on a per capita basis have been
below those for the OECD as a whole and
considerably below the most severely affected
countries. As elsewhere, age has been the key
vulnerability, with around 90% of COVID-19-related
deaths among those aged over 70 years. Also,
racialised minorities have had a higher risk of
COVID-19 infection and mortality. The first wave of
the pandemic was concentrated in Quebec and
Ontario, but case numbers became more
widespread in the second wave. The second wave
has seen provinces and territories selectively
extending and re-imposing limits on activity.
Canada’s mass vaccination began in December,
under a plan that envisages enough vaccine for
every Canadian that wants one by September
2021. Some limits on activity are now being lifted.</FONT>
</P>
<IMAGE>
</IMAGE>
<P>
<FONT font-name="StatLink" font-size="9.00pt">StatLink 2</FONT>
<FONT font-name="ArialNarrow" font-size="9.00pt">https://stat.link/rboyhq</FONT>
</P>
<P>
<FONT font-name="ArialMT" font-size="9.96pt">Those in low-wage jobs, notably young workers,
women and racialised minorities have been hit
hardest economically by the crisis, implying a
potential widening of inequality. In addition, data
confirm deteriorations in mental health during the</FONT>
</P>
<P>
<FONT font-name="ArialMT" font-size="9.96pt">lockdowns. Opioid-related harms and deaths have
risen sharply.</FONT>
</P>
<P>
<BOLD>
<FONT font-name="Arial-BoldMT" font-size="12.00pt">Economic recovery has slowed</FONT>
</BOLD>
</P>
<P>
<BOLD>
<FONT font-name="Arial-BoldMT" font-size="9.96pt">Canada’s economy made a rapid partial
rebound from the spring 2020 confinement but
has since slowed.</FONT>
</BOLD>
<FONT font-name="ArialMT" font-size="9.96pt">Output dropped by more than
15% in the first wave of the pandemic, and the rate
of unemployment spiked up to nearly 14%. The
initial rebound in economic activity was rapid, but
the pace of growth has since diminished. Activity in
the travel, leisure and entertainment sectors
remains well below pre-crisis levels. Output shrank
by 5.4% in 2020.</FONT>
</P>
<IMAGE>
</IMAGE>
<P>
<FONT font-name="StatLink" font-size="9.00pt">StatLink 2</FONT>
<FONT font-name="ArialNarrow" font-size="9.00pt">https://stat.link/37rqua</FONT>
</P>
<P>
<FONT font-name="ArialMT" font-size="9.96pt">Risks and uncertainties remain large, notably
around how quickly restrictions can be lifted as
vaccine rollout proceeds. There are also upside
and downside risks in how rapidly households will
unwind precautionary saving. Volatile global
energy prices have discouraged oil and gas
investment. On the upside, the expected fiscal
stimulus in the United States could bring a large
boost to Canadian exports.</FONT>
</P>
<P>
<FONT font-name="ArialMT" font-size="9.96pt">OECD projections envisage annual output growth
of around 4.7% in 2021 and 4% 2022. This will
bring output close to pre-crisis trends and drive falls
in the rate of unemployment. Headline consumer-</FONT>
</P>
<P>
<FONT font-name="ArialMT" font-size="9.96pt">price inflation will be affected by energy prices in
the near term, core inflation will pick up gradually.</FONT>
</P>
<IMAGE>
</IMAGE>
<P>
<BOLD>
<FONT font-name="Arial-BoldMT" font-size="12.00pt">Continuing monetary support</FONT>
</BOLD>
</P>
<P>
<BOLD>
<FONT font-name="Arial-BoldMT" font-size="9.96pt">An ultra-low policy rate and other monetary
measures continue to provide substantial
support for the economy.</FONT>
</BOLD>
</P>
<P>
<FONT font-name="ArialMT" font-size="9.96pt">The Bank of Canada cut its policy rate to 0.25% in
the early stages of the crisis. The Bank’s forward
guidance on the policy interest rate, reinforced by
its purchases of government securities, have eased
borrowing conditions for households, firms and
governments. Dissipating risks on some fronts
have allowed the Bank to withdraw some liquidity
support introduced at the beginning of the crisis.
The upcoming 2021 renewal of the inflation-
targeting regime provides an opportunity to adapt
the Bank’s monetary policy framework to achieve
its 2 % inflation target, over time, and maintain well-
anchored inflation expectations in the context of
persistently low global policy interest rates and
risks to real-side recovery.</FONT>
</P>
<P>
<FONT font-name="ArialMT" font-size="9.96pt">House prices have been increasing since late
spring, when easing of the initial round of
containment measures began. Household debt
(especially in the form of mortgage borrowing)
remains high, but debt service is less onerous. Low
borrowing costs may also be amplifying already
substantial high-risk corporate bond funding.</FONT>
</P>
<P>
<BOLD>
<FONT font-name="Arial-BoldMT" font-size="12.00pt">Fiscal measures to support a greener
and more inclusive economy</FONT>
</BOLD>
</P>
<P>
<BOLD>
<FONT font-name="Arial-BoldMT" font-size="9.96pt">The priority should be to ensure fiscal policy
provides the best assistance for households
and businesses to recover from the crisis.</FONT>
</BOLD>
</P>
<P>
<FONT font-name="ArialMT" font-size="9.96pt">Canadian governments have acted on a broad front
to bolster demand and assist both households and
businesses. Federal government measures have
accounted for most of the fiscal response, which
has been substantial. Prudent fiscal policy in recent
years has helped provide scope for the large
stimulus.</FONT>
</P>
<P>
<FONT font-name="ArialMT" font-size="9.96pt">A high priority on fiscal support should remain while
the economy is fragile. Crisis-related fiscal support
can be withdrawn as the economy recovers.
Nevertheless, a clear and transparent roadmap for
preventing a spiralling public debt burden is
needed.</FONT>
</P>
<P>
<FONT font-name="ArialMT" font-size="9.96pt">A fiscal roadmap would help accommodate the
need for additional resources in certain areas of
public spending. Solutions to the gaps in socio-
economic support and shortfalls in health care
revealed by the crisis are likely to require additional
resources for the longer term. Furthermore, the
ageing-related spending pressures present before
the pandemic will continue. Accommodating these
fiscal demands in the medium and long term should
be met through either savings in public spending
elsewhere or tax increases.</FONT>
</P>
<IMAGE>
</IMAGE>
<P>
<FONT font-name="StatLink" font-size="9.00pt">StatLink 2</FONT>
<FONT font-name="ArialNarrow" font-size="9.00pt">https://stat.link/digsrf</FONT>
</P>
<P>
<FONT font-name="ArialMT" font-size="9.96pt">There is scope to re-orient the tax system in ways
that would bring structural improvement and
generate some additional revenue. In particular,
Canada’s environmental tax revenues are smaller
relative to GDP than for most other countries. The
carbon price floor needs to steepen if Canada is to
meet its official commitments. Recent federal
government proposals for carbon-price increases</FONT>
</P>
<P>
<FONT font-name="ArialMT" font-size="9.96pt">announced as part of a strengthened climate plan
are encouraging.</FONT>
</P>
<P>
<BOLD>
<FONT font-name="Arial-BoldMT" font-size="12.00pt">Helping business recover and adapt to
the post-COVID economy</FONT>
</BOLD>
</P>
<P>
<BOLD>
<FONT font-name="Arial-BoldMT" font-size="9.96pt">Many businesses continue to struggle, and the
crisis is accelerating structural change in
demand and business operations.</FONT>
</BOLD>
<FONT font-name="ArialMT" font-size="9.96pt">The federal
government should be prepared to step in with
further measures to help businesses. Schemes
offering them credit are welcome, but
encouragement of other forms of financing and
improvement to insolvency procedures should be
considered.</FONT>
</P>
<P>
<FONT font-name="ArialMT" font-size="9.96pt">Non-tariff barriers arising from inter-provincial
differences in product, service and labour market
regulation continue to hamper business activity.
With respect to broadband services, there are
longstanding concerns about the strength of
provider competition, and provision for rural and
remote households, notably for Indigenous
peoples, remains a challenge. Canada scores well
in international indicators of domestic corruption.
However, its property register system is often
exploited for money laundering.</FONT>
</P>
<P>
<BOLD>
<FONT font-name="Arial-BoldMT" font-size="12.00pt">Hard-wiring well-being into
policymaking could help with recovery</FONT>
</BOLD>
</P>
<P>
<BOLD>
<FONT font-name="Arial-BoldMT" font-size="9.96pt">A more structured policy approach to well-
being would help Canada achieve a resilient
and healthy post-COVID economy and society.</FONT>
</BOLD>
<FONT font-name="ArialMT" font-size="9.96pt">The federal government is exploring how to
incorporate a comprehensive dashboard of quality-
of-life measurements into decision-making and
budgeting. Many countries are using such
dashboards, including indicators of individuals’
current and future well-being and, often, measures
of social inclusiveness and environmental
sustainability. Canada is in a strong position to
develop such a dashboard. It has good data on
measures of well-being and has experience in
integrating some dimensions of well-being into
policy through its Gender Based Analysis Plus
(GBA+).</FONT>
</P>
<P>
<FONT font-name="ArialMT" font-size="9.96pt">Once agreed following public consultations, the
dashboard should be hardwired into budgeting so
as to ensure that all government ministries and
agencies base their economic and social policy
reforms on the same criteria. A key choice is</FONT>
</P>
<P>
<FONT font-name="ArialMT" font-size="9.96pt">whether to use the dashboard solely for budget
policy changes or whether to apply it across the
entire tax and spending baseline, as well as for
regulatory impact and cost-benefit analyses.</FONT>
</P>
<P>
<BOLD>
<FONT font-name="Arial-BoldMT" font-size="12.00pt">Strengthening health care and welfare
policy</FONT>
</BOLD>
</P>
<P>
<BOLD>
<FONT font-name="Arial-BoldMT" font-size="9.96pt">COVID-19 has brought to light shortfalls in
Canada’s elderly care and welfare support.</FONT>
</BOLD>
<FONT font-name="ArialMT" font-size="9.96pt">The
initial wave of the pandemic saw around 80% of
COVID-19 fatalities in long-term care facilities and
retirement homes. In addition to highlighting
challenges in containing the virus, this revealed
broader problems in the quality of long-term care.
The pandemic also revealed resource issues for
public health services and has underscored the
downsides of pharmaceuticals not being included
in national public health coverage and Canada’s
limited provisions for sick-leave compensation.</FONT>
</P>
<P>
<FONT font-name="ArialMT" font-size="9.96pt">The crisis has increased the prominence of a
number of socio-economic challenges. Canada’s
gender wage gap for full-time workers is almost 5
percentage points above the OECD average.
Addressing this would be helped by further
progress in improving access to affordable
childcare so that women can pursue fulfilling
careers more easily. In addition, a wider problem of
weak backing for those unemployed or
experiencing poverty remains, despite the recently
implemented National Poverty Strategy.</FONT>
</P>
<P>
<FONT font-name="ArialMT" font-size="9.96pt">Housing affordability and homelessness are key
issues. The prolonged low-interest environment
has contributed to increases in the price of housing.
Social and other forms of affordable housing are
limited, and waiting lists are long. The policy
initiatives underway are welcome, but more could
be done.</FONT>
</P>
<P>
<FONT font-name="ArialMT" font-size="9.96pt">Indigenous peoples remain underprivileged in most
socio-economic dimensions, including income,
employment, security, housing, life expectancy and
physical and mental health. Some progress has
been made in empowering their governments,
including through a distinctions-based approach
that makes greater efforts to tailor policy to each of
the three Indigenous groups, First Nations, Métis
and Inuit. However, a further strengthening of self-
determination is needed, as are more resources to
eliminate gaps with other Canadians.</FONT>
</P>
<IMAGE>
</IMAGE>
</BLOCK2>
</BLOCK1>
<BLOCK1>
<TI>1 Key Policy Insights</TI>
<P>
<FONT font-name="ArialMT" font-size="9.96pt">Contagion and fatalities from COVID-19 have been less severe in Canada than in the hardest-hit countries,
and vaccine rollout is underway. However, the economy remains heavily affected by the crisis with the
latest round of containment measures slowing the recovery in activity and employment (Figure 1.1). The
crisis has highlighted economic and social strengths. Canada’s federal system of government proved
capable of a rapid and co-ordinated policy response. Low public debt prior to the crisis has helped provide
headroom for substantial tax and spending measures. The acceleration in teleworking and use of online
services during the crisis has opened the door to new ways of working and living for the future. Reduced
noise and air pollution during confinement raised environmental awareness. The prospect of a structural
downshift in demand and employment in some sectors is creating potential for more green jobs and
investment.</FONT>
</P>
<P>
<FONT font-name="ArialMT" font-size="9.96pt">COVID-19 has also highlighted weak points and brought new issues. In health care, the pandemic has
shone a light on shortfalls in the quality of some of Canada’s long-term residential care homes, co-
ordination difficulties in public health and the absence of common nationwide pharmaceutical coverage.
Concerns have emerged about the effects of prolonged restrictions on social interaction and mental health.
The concentration of layoffs in low-wage jobs has underscored that this downturn has widened economic
inequalities. Also, gaps in income support among those losing jobs and income have been exposed. The
crisis has heightened the prominence of other socio-economic challenges, including vulnerabilities among
low-skill, low-income households, Indigenous peoples and racialised groups.</FONT>
</P>
<P>
<FONT font-name="ArialMT" font-size="9.96pt">The key messages of this</FONT>
<FONT font-name="Arial,Italic" font-size="9.96pt">
<EM>Economic Survey</EM>
</FONT>
<FONT font-name="ArialMT" font-size="9.96pt">are:</FONT>
</P>
<BLOCK2 LABEL="Table">
<TMPTABLE>
<SGMLTBL>
<TBLHEAD TBLWD="600">
<TBLCDEFS COLSEP="VSINGLE" HALIGN="CENTER" CHARPOS="75%" TOPSEP="HSINGLE">
<TBLCDEF COLWD="100" TBLUNITS="PERCENT" />
</TBLCDEFS>
<TBLROWS ROWSEP="HSINGLE" VALIGN="TOP" LEFTSEP="VSINGLE">
<TBLROW>
<TBLCELL ROWSEP="HSINGLE" COLSTART="1">
<FONT font-name="ArialMT" font-size="9.96pt">Canada’s economy remains vulnerable in the ongoing COVID-19 crisis. There are
substantial risks and uncertainties, and potentially deep scars to some sectors.
Fiscal policy should continue to prioritise bolstering economic recovery but also
prepare the groundwork for containing public debt when the recovery is well under
way. With the prospect of prolonged ultra-low interest rates, asset-price inflation
and high investor risk-taking add to medium-term concerns.</FONT>
</TBLCELL>
</TBLROW>
</TBLROWS>
</TBLHEAD>
<TBLBODY TBLWD="600">
<TBLCDEFS COLSEP="VSINGLE" HALIGN="CENTER" CHARPOS="75%" TOPSEP="HSINGLE">
<TBLCDEF COLWD="100" TBLUNITS="PERCENT" />
</TBLCDEFS>
<TBLROWS ROWSEP="HSINGLE" VALIGN="TOP" LEFTSEP="VSINGLE">
<TBLROW>
<TBLCELL ROWSEP="HSINGLE" COLSTART="1">
<FONT font-name="ArialMT" font-size="9.96pt">Canadian policy makers need to maintain a balanced perspective across income,
health, social conditions and the environment if well-being is to improve. Attention
to distributional issues, including inequality, inclusiveness and disadvantage are
also central to societal well-being. Canadian governments should hardwire the well-
being perspective into the policy-making processes.</FONT>
</TBLCELL>
</TBLROW>
<TBLROW>
<TBLCELL ROWSEP="HSINGLE" COLSTART="1">
<FONT font-name="ArialMT" font-size="9.96pt">Nurturing recovery and transition in the business sector is key to a successful post-
pandemic economy and society. Policy needs to continue encouraging transition to
a greener economy. Canada’s longstanding structural impediments to business
efficiency also need addressing.</FONT>
</TBLCELL>
</TBLROW>
</TBLROWS>
</TBLBODY>
</SGMLTBL>
</TMPTABLE>
</BLOCK2>
<IMAGE>
</IMAGE>
<P>
<FONT font-name="StatLink" font-size="9.00pt">StatLink 2</FONT>
<FONT font-name="ArialNarrow" font-size="9.00pt">https://stat.link/quic5f</FONT>
</P>
<P>
<BOLD>
<FONT font-name="Arial-BoldMT" font-size="12.00pt">Vaccine rollout is underway</FONT>
</BOLD>
</P>
<P>
<FONT font-name="ArialMT" font-size="9.96pt">Canada’s first cases of COVID-19 appeared in mid-January 2020, with substantial acceleration in cases
from early March (Figure 1.2). However, the initial wave of the pandemic in Canada was not as severe as
that seen in some other countries. Daily COVID-19 cases in the second wave have exceeded those of the
first, while fatalities reached similar levels. The first wave of the pandemic was concentrated in Ontario
and, especially, Québec, which had the largest number of fatalities in absolute terms and on a per capital
basis. The second wave saw per-capita cases and fatalities surge again in Québec and Ontario, but also
in other provinces, notably in Alberta and Manitoba (Government of Canada, 2020).</FONT>
</P>
<P>
<FONT font-name="ArialMT" font-size="9.96pt">As elsewhere, older adults, especially those with underlying medical conditions, have been more at risk of
contracting COVID-19 and developing severe complications. Around 90% of COVID-19-related deaths
have been among those aged over 70 years (Government of Canada, 2020). The spread of the virus in
care homes has been a key concern and the crisis has revealed instances of poor quality care and
overcrowding. Echoing developments in some other countries, racialised minorities have had higher risk
of COVID-19 infection and mortality (racialisation is a term used for when groups come to be socially
constructed as races, based on characteristics such as race, ethnicity, language, economics, religion,
culture and politics). Explanatory factors include high poverty rates, over-representation in socio-
economically disadvantaged neighbourhoods, crowded housing conditions and disproportionate numbers
working in occupations at risk of exposure to the virus (Statistics Canada, 2020a). In addition, surveys
confirm deteriorating mental health during the lockdowns (Statistics Canada, 2020b), with social isolation,
loneliness and increasing substance use playing a role.</FONT>
</P>
<P>
<FONT font-name="ArialMT" font-size="9.96pt">The initial phase of containment measures came into force from mid to late March. Provinces and territories
played a central role given their responsibilities in health care and public health (Box 1.1). States of
emergency and other measures brought school closure, regulation on distancing, operational restrictions
on various types of businesses, and public health advice for people to stay at home. These measures
started to unwind in May and June under provincial re-opening plans. In the second wave of the pandemic
provinces and territories selectively extended and re-imposed limits on activity (often at a localised level),
as well as strengthened public-health requirements and testing capacities. As of February 2021 some
restrictions were being lifted in the wake of declining caseloads and fatalities.</FONT>
</P>
<IMAGE>
</IMAGE>
<P>
<FONT font-name="StatLink" font-size="9.00pt">StatLink 2</FONT>
<FONT font-name="ArialNarrow" font-size="9.00pt">https://stat.link/blqt69</FONT>
</P>
<P>
<FONT font-name="ArialMT" font-size="9.96pt">Roll-out of mass vaccination began in mid-December following approval of a vaccine shortly beforehand.
Canada’s immunisation plan envisages sufficient supply to vaccinate 3 million people by the end of the
first quarter of 2021 (i.e. around 8% of the population) and enough supply for all Canadians who want to
be vaccinated by September (Public Health Agency of Canada, 2020).</FONT>
</P>
<P>
<FONT font-name="ArialMT" font-size="9.96pt">A clear picture is yet to emerge of what has determined the course of the pandemic in Canada relative to
other countries, and the reasons for the substantial differences across provinces and territories. Low
population and housing density compared with, for instance, many European countries may be part of the
explanation. Differences in containment policies and in the public’s response to them are also likely to be
a factor explaining how the pandemic has spread. For instance, OECD work points to the efficacy of test-
trace-isolate policy, so differences across countries, and within them, on this front are probably affecting
outcomes (OECD, 2020a). The strength of sanctions for non-compliance of quarantine measures may also
be playing a role. Québec, for instance, introduced very high maximum penalties: CAN 750 000 and up to
six months in prison. Also, as exemplified by the long-term care issues mentioned above, capacities and
vulnerabilities in the health-care system influence rates of infection and recovery. There is scope for other</FONT>
</P>
<P>
<FONT font-name="ArialMT" font-size="9.96pt">factors: some research suggests the earlier timing of Québec’s March school break compared with
Ontario’s brought accelerated infection from returning travellers (Godin et al., 2020).</FONT>
</P>
<IMAGE>
</IMAGE>
<P>
<FONT font-name="ArialMT" font-size="9.96pt">Confinement and other public-health measures taken in spring 2020 resulted in a drop in gross domestic
product in excess of 15% between February and April. Most sectors experienced substantial output
reductions. And, as expected, retail, travel, leisure and entertainment-related activities were especially
hard hit from the combination of supply disruptions and weak demand. In addition, construction and many
other sectors suffered supply issues from manufacturing stoppages, and some have also struggled to get
a significant portion of workforces back to work.</FONT>
</P>
<P>
<FONT font-name="ArialMT" font-size="9.96pt">Canada has taken many steps to head off macroeconomic instability, bolster demand and support
households and businesses (Table 1.1). The Bank of Canada responded with cuts in its policy rate and
measures to bolster liquidity and financial markets. Federal-government actions have accounted for most
of the fiscal response. Containment of the public-debt burden through prudent fiscal policy in the years
prior to the pandemic has helped provide scope for a large stimulus. Federal outlays on direct support
measures are estimated at 12% of GDP, which is among the largest packages announced by OECD
governments (Figure 1.3, Table 1.1). Estimates suggest that the fiscal package will have bolstered output
by around 5 percentage points of GDP in both 2020 and 2021, implying a considerably smaller increase
in unemployment than would have occurred otherwise (Figure 1.4).</FONT>
</P>
<IMAGE>
</IMAGE>
<IMAGE>
</IMAGE>
<P>
<FONT font-name="StatLink" font-size="9.00pt">StatLink 2</FONT>
<FONT font-name="ArialNarrow" font-size="9.00pt">https://stat.link/q63u4a</FONT>
</P>
<IMAGE>
</IMAGE>
<P>
<FONT font-name="StatLink" font-size="9.00pt">StatLink 2</FONT>
<FONT font-name="ArialNarrow" font-size="9.00pt">https://stat.link/pzec9b</FONT>
</P>
<P>
<FONT font-name="ArialMT" font-size="9.96pt">Central to the support measures have been the Canada Emergency Response Benefit (CERB), and its
successors (notably the Canada Recovery Benefits, CRB), along with the Canada Emergency Wage
Subsidy (CEWS). According to government estimates (Table 1.1), these programmes will cost CAD 190
billion, around 70% of the total spend on direct support measures. CERB provided income support for
workers across all sectors losing income and employment due to COVID-19. It expired in September 2020
and was partially replaced by more targeted schemes. The need for CERB’s introduction raised questions
regarding the adequacy of income support in Canada (discussed further below). A continuing role is
anticipated for the CEWS scheme – it has been extended until mid-2021. Other federal measures for
businesses include rental subsidies, credit support and loan guarantees (many have also been extended
into 2021). Federal government also introduced provisions for banks to offer mortgage deferrals to
households.</FONT>
</P>
<P>
<FONT font-name="ArialMT" font-size="9.96pt">Provincial and territorial governments have been doing the heavy lifting on the health response, while the
federal government has provided most of the economic support. Accordingly, the scale of provincial and
territorial government economic-support measures has been comparatively small. Outlays are estimated
at around 1% of GDP. Provincial governments have provided supplementary safety nets for households.
For instance, Ontario introduced an emergency assistance benefit and Alberta a one-off payment for those
isolating. Québec has introduced a temporary aid programme for employees not covered by other
schemes. Provinces also introduced eviction moratoria for renters. Assistance for business has included
payment deferral of provincially administered taxes (Ontario, Alberta and British Columbia), deferrals of
utility bills (British Columbia), and subsidies covering the fixed costs of businesses affected by public-
health restrictions (Québec).</FONT>
</P>
<P>
<BOLD>
<FONT font-name="Arial-BoldMT" font-size="12.00pt">The economy is recovering, but the pace has slowed and risks remain elevated</FONT>
</BOLD>
</P>
<P>
<FONT font-name="ArialMT" font-size="9.96pt">With the beginning of the lifting of restrictions in May 2020, activity picked up sharply. By August, real GDP
was around 5% below the pre-crisis level. The substantial monetary and fiscal support played an important
role in bolstering household incomes and enabling businesses to survive lockdown. The household saving
ratio soared in the early phase of the crisis, driven by limited consumption opportunities due to lockdowns
and increased precautionary saving but also by the policy support to household incomes.</FONT>
</P>
<P>
<FONT font-name="ArialMT" font-size="9.96pt">Continued constraints on economic activity and the strengthening of some public-health measures due to
the second wave of the pandemic have slowed the pace of economic recovery. The rate of monthly output
growth declined substantially by the end of 2020 (Figure 1.5) with a halt to recovery in manufacturing and
construction and renewed decline in some service sectors (Figure 1.6). Uncertainty on economic prospects
is affecting households and businesses. The end of payment-deferral provisions, notably in taxation and
mortgage payments, has not so far prompted critical problems but will nevertheless have impacted
household finances.</FONT>
</P>
<IMAGE>
</IMAGE>
<P>
<FONT font-name="StatLink" font-size="9.00pt">StatLink 2</FONT>
<FONT font-name="ArialNarrow" font-size="9.00pt">https://stat.link/7jg5hk</FONT>
</P>
<P>
<FONT font-name="ArialMT" font-size="9.96pt">Unemployment is still elevated and has recently been increasing. Canada’s rate of unemployment was
8.7% in the fourth quarter of 2020, in the upper half of OECD countries and high compared with the pre-
crisis level of just over 5% (Figure 1.7). Echoing the impact of renewed confinement measures,
employment has fallen markedly in some service sectors since the end of 2020 impacting employment
among young people in particular (Figure 1.8). An OECD survey reveals that young people see
employment and disposable-income concerns arising from COVID-19 as the most challenging issues for
them, along with mental health (OECD, 2020b).</FONT>
</P>
<IMAGE>
</IMAGE>
<P>
<FONT font-name="StatLink" font-size="9.00pt">StatLink 2</FONT>
<FONT font-name="ArialNarrow" font-size="9.00pt">https://stat.link/zawcqn</FONT>
</P>
<IMAGE>
</IMAGE>
<IMAGE>
</IMAGE>
<P>
<FONT font-name="StatLink" font-size="9.00pt">StatLink 2</FONT>
<FONT font-name="ArialNarrow" font-size="9.00pt">https://stat.link/hbvf4z</FONT>
</P>
<P>
<FONT font-name="ArialMT" font-size="9.96pt">In the initial months of the crisis, consumer-price inflation slowed, but house-price growth picked up after
the relaxation of the first round of containment measures. The large fall in oil prices in the early stages of
the pandemic had a substantial impact on consumer-price inflation (Figure 1.9), and also the price of
accommodation fell substantially (discussed further below). Meanwhile, in the housing market lower
interest rates have encouraged demand, and government income support and mortgage-payment
deferrals have limited forced sales, contributing to an increase in prices (Figure 1.10). In addition, time
spent at home during lockdown and the prospect of a permanent shift to more teleworking may have
ramped up demand for first-time purchases and upgrades (Statistics Canada, 2020c). With the end of
mortgage-payment deferrals and the emergence of longer-term effects on household finances, it is likely
that price growth will soften. A moderate house price correction would be welcome, given the longstanding
concern that prices may be over-inflated (Box 1.2) and the affordability challenges that were already
evident prior to the pandemic (Chapter 2). Also, moderate correction in the near term would reduce the
risk of a large and destabilising price adjustment later on (discussed further below).</FONT>
</P>
<IMAGE>
</IMAGE>
<P>
<FONT font-name="StatLink" font-size="9.00pt">StatLink 2</FONT>
<FONT font-name="ArialNarrow" font-size="9.00pt">https://stat.link/qmdj01</FONT>
</P>
<IMAGE>
</IMAGE>
<P>
<FONT font-name="StatLink" font-size="9.00pt">StatLink 2</FONT>
<FONT font-name="ArialNarrow" font-size="9.00pt">https://stat.link/nrs3gf</FONT>
</P>
<P>
<FONT font-name="ArialMT" font-size="9.96pt">Annual output growth of 4.7% is projected for the Canadian economy in 2021 and 4% 2022 (Table 1.2).
Continued weakness is expected in the near term until the fall in COVID-19 caseloads and progress in
vaccination allow most restrictions to be unwound. Reduced constraints on supply and the release of pent-
up demand will bring strong growth in the second half of 2021, with a substantial carry over effect to growth
in 2022. These developments will be echoed in the labour market. Growth in underlying consumer prices
will pick up gradually.</FONT>
</P>
<IMAGE>
</IMAGE>
<IMAGE>
</IMAGE>
<P>
<BOLD>
<FONT font-name="Arial-BoldItalicMT" font-size="11.04pt">
<EM>Risks and uncertainties are elevated</EM>
</FONT>
</BOLD>
</P>
<P>
<FONT font-name="ArialMT" font-size="9.96pt">Although vaccine roll-out is underway, there is uncertainty on the speed of deployment, and, related to
this, uncertainty on how quickly containment measures can be lifted. This relates to another key
uncertainty, the speed with which the household sector will ramp up consumption spending as the
pandemic subsides, running down the savings accumulated during the confinements. In addition, fall-out
from hard-hit sectors may affect the economy more than expected. The leisure, travel and entertainment
sectors comprise only a small share of Canada’s GDP. However, in the event of widespread bankruptcies,
the rest of the economy may struggle to absorb the layoffs. Furthermore, activities with links to the hard-
hit sectors, such as aircraft manufacture, are affected. In addition, there are structural impacts whose scale
is uncertain, including the accelerated shift to online retail and the possibility of permanent downshift in
commuting and travel. The significant government support still being provided to households and
businesses will help offset these risks. Among the upside risks, the expected fiscal stimulus in the United
States could bring a substantial a boost to Canadian exports.</FONT>
</P>
<P>
<FONT font-name="ArialMT" font-size="9.96pt">Trade tensions, a risk prior to COVID-19, continue. Canada’s economic recovery from the pandemic crisis
will depend substantially on developments in the United States, given the close economic ties between the
two countries. The conclusion of the United States-Mexico-Canada Agreement (USMCA) has reduced
uncertainty for much of Canada’s international trade (Box 1.3). However, the Agreement’s 16-year sunset
implies uncertainty for the long term. Furthermore, global trade tensions and uncertainties are still elevated.
Although political changes in the United States and some European trade partners bring the prospect of
contributing to improved global trade relations, risks remain (e.g., uncertainty about the trajectory of
China’s trade policies). For example, Canada’s trade relations with China have seen a number of
developments since the previous</FONT>
<FONT font-name="Arial,Italic" font-size="9.96pt">
<EM>Survey</EM>
</FONT>
<FONT font-name="ArialMT" font-size="9.96pt">, including blocks by China on sales of pork and beef and
suspension of the licenses of Canadian canola exporters in 2019.</FONT>
</P>
<IMAGE>
</IMAGE>
<IMAGE>
</IMAGE>
<P>
<FONT font-name="ArialMT" font-size="9.96pt">Pre-crisis macro-financial risks relating to housing debt and corporate-bond financing are in some respects
greater. Government support measures have gone a long way in preventing widespread financial problems
among highly indebted households. However, the earnings prospects for many households will remain
weakened for some time, raising default risk. Because household debt is large, the impact of any future
weakening of income growth implies a significant impact on household consumption. Furthermore, the
economic downturn may expose the fragilities of the significant share of low-grade corporate debt. The
prospect of an even more prolonged low interest-rate environment gives cause for continued concern
about investor risk-taking and asset valuations and their distributional implications (discussed further
below).</FONT>
</P>
<IMAGE>
</IMAGE>
<P>
<BOLD>
<FONT font-name="Arial-BoldMT" font-size="12.00pt">Challenges for monetary policy and financial-sector stability</FONT>
</BOLD>
</P>
<P>
<FONT font-name="ArialMT" font-size="9.96pt">A rapid policy response in the early stages of the crisis, through policy-rate cuts and other measures that
bolster liquidity, helped Canada avoid a financial-market meltdown. The Bank of Canada used practically
all the scope for rate cuts (while remaining in positive territory), cutting the policy rate to 0.25%, the same
as that in the aftermath of the global financial crisis (Figure 1.12). This was accompanied by other
measures to provide liquidity and ensure financial markets continued to function (Table 1.4). These were
broadly successful. By May 2020, market liquidity for federal-government bonds, provincial debt and
corporate paper had returned to pre-crisis levels. In addition, funding pressures on banks have receded
(Bank of Canada, 2020a). The Bank’s forward guidance on the policy interest rate reinforced by its
purchases of government securities has also eased borrowing conditions for households, firms and
governments. The purchases of government securities has resulted in a substantial increase in the Bank’s
balance sheet (Figure 1.13).</FONT>
</P>
<P>
<BOLD>
<FONT font-name="Arial-BoldItalicMT" font-size="11.04pt">
<EM>Ultra-accommodative monetary policy can, and should, be maintained until the economy
is on an even keel</EM>
</FONT>
</BOLD>
</P>
<P>
<FONT font-name="ArialMT" font-size="9.96pt">In the initial phase of the crisis, assessing consumer price inflation was complicated by the diverse effects
on prices in different segments of the economy. The large fall in crude oil prices early in the crisis pushed
down gasoline prices. Also, the price of accommodation fell. Meanwhile, retail food prices rose. Shifts in
purchasing patterns were significant, but Bank of Canada research suggests that accounting for these did
not generate a substantially different picture of overall price developments (Bank of Canada, 2020b).</FONT>
</P>
<IMAGE>
</IMAGE>
<P>
<FONT font-name="StatLink" font-size="9.00pt">StatLink 2</FONT>
<FONT font-name="ArialNarrow" font-size="9.00pt">https://stat.link/ft7q4g</FONT>
</P>
</BLOCK1>
</FREEFORM>
</POLIDOC>
</ROOT>